Guide to the Hartt School of Music Public Relations ICAM records ARCH119
University of Hartford Archives & Special Collections
Hartt School of Music Public Relations ICAM records
1948-1981
University of Hartford Archives & Special Collections
Hartt School of Music. Public Relations
ARCH119
1.67 Linear Feet (4 containers)
Conditions Governing Access
The collection is open to all researchers.
Biographical / Historical
The Institute of Contemporary American Music, often abbreviated as ICAM, was founded in 1948-1949 by Hartt faculty member and composer Isadore Freed. Led and organized by members of the Hartt faculty, the annual festivals featured the original work of contemporary composers in a series of concerts—sometimes contained within two days, other times spread out as a series throughout the academic year.
Composers highlighted by the annual festivals have represented a diversity of styles, regions, genres, and ages, many of whom were able to attend the performances of their works. The Institute, as it was sometimes called, has been host to such routine names as Randall Thompson, Elliott Carter, and Aaron Copland, as well as premiering many works of composers of lesser fame. Hartt composers who have had their works performed and/or premiered at an ICAM festival include Isadore Freed, Arnold Franchetti, Thomas Putsche, and Edward Diemente. Many of the guest composers have also served the Hartt community by coaching young composers and presenting lectures at the festivals.
Often, the festivals would center around a specific theme in an attempt to unite the works presented. Themes for festivals have included geographic regions (Midwest 1956-1957, Far West 1957-1958, Southwest 1958-1959); composers from a particular country (Canada 1959-1960, Israel 1972-1973), and concerts centered around the work of one specific composer, (Isadore Freed 1960-1961, Arnold Franchetti 1966-1967, Aaron Copland 1970-1971, Charles Ives 1974-1975, Elliott Carter 1978-1979, Gunther Schuller 1979-1980)
Scope and Contents
Records in this collection contain a combination of programs from the festivals, newspaper clippings and publicity materials, professional headshots and biographies of the composers, correspondence with guests and the press, and drafts of press releases and program layouts.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged into two series: I. Programs and Publicity and II. Photographs.
Institute of Contemporary American Music; Photographs; concert programs; Music festivals; Music -- United States; Composition (Music); Composers; Julius Hartt School of Music; Hartt College of Music; Hartt School of Music; Freed, Isadore, 1900-1960; Franchetti, Arnold, 1906-1993; Putsché, Thomas, 1929-1983; Diemente, Edward
- Programs and Publicity, 1948 - 1981; I
  Scope and Contents
  This series contains concert programs, as well as publicity related materials including newspaper clippings, small scrapbooks, press releases, and correspondence with concert participants and planners.
  Arrangement
  The series is arranged chronologically by season.
  - 1st Season, 1948 - 1949 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - 2nd Season, 1949 - 1950 (Box 1, Folder 2-4)
  - 3rd Season, 1950 - 1951 (Box 1, Folder 5-6)
  - 4th Season, 1951 - 1952 (Box 1, Folder 8-9)
  - 5th Season, 1952 - 1953 (Box 1, Folder 10-11)
  - 6th Season: Macdowell Colony Composers' Festival, 1953 - 1954 (Box 1, Folder 12-13)
    A signed letter from Aaron Copland is included in this file.
  - 7th Season: Young Composers' Festival, 1954 - 1955 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - 8th Season: Yaddo Composers' Festival, 1955 - 1956 (Box 1, Folder 15-17)
  - 9th Season: Midwestern Composers' Festival, 1956 - 1957 (Box 1, Folder 18-19)
  - 10th Season: Far Western Composers' Festival, 1957 - 1958 (Box 1, Folder 20-21)
  - 11th Season: South Western Composers Festival, 1958 - 1959 (Box 1, Folder 22-25)
    The file includes The Courant Magazine article "Hartford's Coming Composers" (Nov 23, 1958) and documentation for the article which discusses the institute and composers at Hartt College.
  - 12th Season: Canadian Composers' Festival, 1959 - 1960 (Box 1, Folder 26-28)
  - 13th Season: In Memoriam Isadore Freed, 1960 - 1961 (Box 2, Folder 1-3)
  - 14th Season, 1961 - 1962 (Box 2, Folder 4-5)
  - 15th Season, 1962 - 1963 (Box 2, Folder 6-9)
  - 16th Season, 1963 - 1964 (Box 2, Folder 10-12)
  - 17th Season, 1964 - 1965 (Box 2, Folder 13-15)
  - 18th Season, 1965 - 1966 (Box 2, Folder 16-17)
  - 19th Season: Arnold Franchetti, 1966 - 1967 (Box 2, Folder 18-19)
  - 20th Anniversary Season, 1967 - 1968 (Box 2, Folder 20-22)
  - 21st Season: Czechoslovakian Composers, 1968 - 1969 (Box 3, Folder 1-4)
  - 22nd Season: Festival of Tape Music and Mixed Media, 1969 - 1970 (Box 3, Folder 5-6)
  - 23rd Season: Aaron Copland's 70th, 1970 - 1971 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - 24th Season, 1971 - 1972 (Box 3, Folder 8-10)
  - 25th Season: Israeli Composers' Festival, 1972 - 1973 (Box 3, Folder 11-14)
  - 26th Season: Ives Centennial, 1974 - 1975 (Box 3, Folder 15-16)
  - 27th Season, 1975 - 1976 (Box 3, Folder 17-18)
  - 28th Season, 1976 - 1977 (Box 3, Folder 19-20)
  - 30th Anniversary Season, 1977 - 1978 (Box 4, Folder 1-2)
  - 31st Season, 1978 - 1979 (Box 4, Folder 3-6)
    This file also includes the Eliott Carter Retrospective On the Composer's 70th Birthday.
  - Award of Merit, 1979 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - 32nd Season, 1979 - 1980 (Box 4, Folder 8-9)
  - Student Composers' Contest, 1979 - 1980 (Box 4, Folder 10-11)
  - 33rd Season, 1980 - 1981 (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - Raphael Valerio and Thou America, undated (Box 4, Folder 13)
  - History-General Overview, undated (Box 4, Folder 14)
- Photographs, 1948 - 1980; II
  The photograph series contains primarily headshots of individuals' who participated in ICAM for promotional purposes, but also includes photographs with Hartt faculty and performances.
  The files in this series are arranged chronologically by ICAM season.
  - Season 1, 1948 - 1949 (Box 4, Folder 15)
  - Season 2, 1949 - 1950 (Box 4, Folder 16)
  - Season 3, 1950 - 1951 (Box 4, Folder 17)
  - Season 4, 1951 - 1952 (Box 4, Folder 18)
  - Season 5, 1952 - 1953 (Box 4, Folder 19)
  - Season 8, 1955 - 1956 (Box 4, Folder 20)
  - Season 9, 1956 - 1957 (Box 4, Folder 21)
  - Season 10, 1957 - 1958 (Box 4, Folder 22)
  - Season 11, 1958 - 1959 (Box 4, Folder 23)
  - Season 11 Coming Composers, 1958 - 1959 (Box 4, Folder 24)
  - Season 13, 1960 - 1961 (Box 4, Folder 25)
  - Season 14, 1961 - 1962 (Box 4, Folder 26)
  - Seaon 16, 1963 - 1964 (Box 4, Folder 27)
  - Season 17, 1964 - 1965 (Box 4, Folder 28)
  - 20th Anniversary Season, 1967 - 1968 (Box 4, Folder 29)
  - Season 21, 1968 - 1969 (Box 4, Folder 30)
  - Season 22, 1969 - 1970 (Box 4, Folder 31)
  - Season 23, 1970 - 1971 (Box 4, Folder 32)
  - Season 25, 1972 - 1973 (Box 4, Folder 33)
  - Season 26, 1974 - 1975 (Box 4, Folder 34)
  - Season 28, 1976 - 1977 (Box 4, Folder 35)
  - Season 30, 1977 - 1978 (Box 4, Folder 36)
  - Season 31, 1978 - 1979 (Box 4, Folder 37)
  - Season 31 Elliott Carter Retrospective, 1978 - 1979 (Box 4, Folder 38)
  - Season 32, 1979 - 1980 (Box 4, Folder 39)
  - Various Photographs, undated (Box 4, Folder 40)